Documenting Lesbian Lives Oral History Project oral histories SSC.MS.00661
Sophia Smith Collection
Documenting Lesbian Lives Oral History Project oral histories
2010-2019
Sophia Smith Collection
SSC.MS.00661
10.75 linear feet (26 containers)
8,456‬ Gigabytes 853 digital files (video, audio, and transcripts)
Documenting Lesbian Lives Oral History Project is a collection of life histories of women who identify as lesbian, bisexual, woman-identified-woman, queer, or who prefer not to identify with sexuality categories. The project provides a complex and nuanced collective story of American lesbian history and experience. Narrators include grassroots activists and political organizers; educators and academics; musicians, writers, and artists; as well as community and religious leaders. They come from a variety of class, ethnic, racial, social, and geographic backgrounds. Interviews cover childhood and growing up experiences; education and employment; activism and politics; family, identity, relationships and community.
Biographical / Historical
Interviews were conducted by Smith College students in Kelly Anderson's "Documenting Lesbian Lives" course beginning in the spring of 2010. Students were trained in both United States lesbian history and oral history techniques and protocols.
Scope and Contents
Documenting Lesbian Lives Oral History Project is a collection of life histories of women who identify as lesbian, bisexual, woman-identified-woman, queer, or who prefer not to identify with sexuality categories. The project provides a complex and nuanced collective story of American lesbian history and experience. Narrators include grassroots activists and political organizers; educators and academics; musicians, writers, and artists; as well as community and religious leaders. They come from a variety of class, ethnic, racial, social, and geographic backgrounds. Interviews cover childhood and growing up experiences; education and employment; activism and politics; family, identity, relationships and community.
Narrators include:
Ackelsberg, Martha
Barale, Michelle
Boggis, Terry
Browne, Karen
Chapman, Mare
Choi, Gina-Kamas
Collier, Chris
Cooke, Carla
Cote, Carol
Davenport, Kate
DiNardo, Geri
Dobkin, Alix
Earley, Deborah
Elkin, Marty
Entwistle, BJ
Essery, Wendy
Evans, Judith
Everhart, Jan
Faison, Deborah
Flachs, Julie
Fusco, Lisa
Gillespie, Peggy
Hackler, Ann
Hairston, Andrea
Harris, Janet
Harris, Lori
Heller, Deborah
Howland, Pam
Irvine, Janice
Jerome, Judith
Kavanaugh, Karla
Laird, Joan
Lanzillotto, Annie
Lathrop, Janet
Lukens, Rebecca
McClintock, Mary
McHaelen, Robin
Millington, June
Morningstar, Betty
Myles, Eileen
Nelson, Kristi
O'Donovan, Alice
Oglesby, Carole
Pato, Roberta
Penotte, Cody
Perez, David
Pittman, Catherine
Plaskow, Judith
Power, Bet
Quinones, Carmen
Rees, Kelly
Richardson, Holly
Ruffino, Renee
Shaw, Peggy
Shaw, Rebecca
Shumsky, Ellen
Spitzer, Rabbi Toba
Sullivan, Laura
Toole, Jay
Walters, Jennifer
Wolfe, Kate
Young, Nanci
Conditions Governing Access
See individual interviews in resource record for specific restrictions on access.
Additional Formats
Full transcripts and streaming video of many interviews are available online to the Smith campus community. Researchers may also request copies of electronic transcripts or video files.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
The Documenting Lesbian Lives Oral History Project was donated to the Sophia Smith Collection by Kelly Anderson and her students beginning in 2010. Annual additions are expected and may not be reflected in this record.
Related Materials
The Sophia Smith Collection The SSC holds the papers of the following: Martha Ackelsberg; Carole Oglesby; Judith Plaskow; Ellen Shumsky; and Women's Music Collection (June Millington).
Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements
This collection contains materials received in digital form that are not currently available online. Please consult with Special Collections staff to request access to this digital content. As a preservation measure, researchers must use digital copies of audiovisual materials in this collection.
Lesbian artists -- United States -- Biography -- Sources; Lesbian mothers -- United States; Lesbianism -- United States -- History -- 20th century -- Sources; Lesbians -- United States -- Biography -- Sources; Lesbian activists; Artists; Writers; Musicians; Professors; Educators; Political activist; Grassroots organizers; Radicals; Electronic records; Videotapes; DVD video discs; Computer media; Oral histories; Transcripts; Bisexuality-United States-History--20th century; Lesbian feminism--United States--History--Sources; Ackelsberg, Martha; Barale, Michelle; Boggis, Terry; Browne, Karen; Chapman, Mare; Choi, Gina-Kamas; Collier, Chris; Cooke, Carla; Cote, Carol; Davenport, Kate; Dobkin, Alix; Earley, Deborah; Elkin, Marty; Essery, Wendy; Evans, Judith; Everhart, Jan; Faison, Deborah; Flachs, Julie; Fusco, Lisa; Gillespie, Peggy; Hackler, Ann; Hairston, Andrea; Harris, Janet; Harris, Lori; Heller, Deborah; Howland, Pam; Irvine, Janice; Jerome, Judith; Kavanaugh, Karla; Laird, Joan; Lanzillotto, Annie; Lathrop, Janet; Lukens, Rebecca; McClintock, Mary; McHaelen, Robin; Millington, June; Morningstar, Betty; Myles, Eileen; Nelson, Kristi; O'Donovan, Alice; Oglesby, Carole A.; Pato, Roberta; Penotte, Cody; Perez, David; Pittman, Catherine; Plaskow, Judith; Power, Bet; Quinones, Carmen; Rees, Kelly; Richardson, Holly; Ruffino, Renee; Shaw, Peggy; Shaw, Rebecca; Shumsky, Ellen; Spitzer, Rabbi Toba; Sullivan, Laura; Toole, Jay; Walters, Jennifer; Wolfe, Kate; Young, Nanci; Ahl, Brenda; Barale, Michele; Beyer, Dana; Brook, Lis; Coleman, Penny; DiNardo, Geri; Dorthee; Elliston, Lelia; Entwisle, BJ; Fagan, Sharon; Faucher, Dawn; Ferguson, Ann; Fisher, Alexandra; Foss, Elizabeth Anne; Gabriner, Vicki; Gensler, Sharon; Gold, Joyce; Greene, Emily; Herbert, Barbara; Higgins, Clare; Hopkins, Lee Ann; Jenkins, Connie; Kaufman, Miriam; Litchford, Marge; LW; MacKenzie, Amy; Madsen, Catherine; Margolies, Liz; McKenzie, Leslie; Moore, Anne; Oglesby, Carole; O'Rourke, Jane; Orrell, L. (pseud.); Ouellette, Savanna; Paglia, Camille; Perez, Davis; Pittnam, Catherine; Powell, Mary Clare; Robinson, Beth; Rorabacher, Wisty; Rosel, Deliah; Schiano, Rita; Schneider, Lesley; Shapiro, Jodie; Zimmerman, Perri Nerri; Yanoshak, Nancy; Winters, Marianne; Stinson, Susan; Stewart, Pamela; Stangl, Jane; Spring-Moore, Michele; Spitzer, Rabbi Tobah; Sorrell, J.M.; Sohodsky, Constance (Barrett); Caurant, Beth; Gottlieb, Paula; Holland, Patricia G.; Innes, E. Carolyn
- Documenting Lesbian Lives, 2010; 27 Gigabytes (62 digital video and text files)
  - Martha Ackelsberg interviewed by Julie Colatrella, 2010 April 16; Ackelsberg, Martha; 1 oral histories (transcript and video)
    Conditions Governing Access
    Biographical / Historical
    Martha A. Ackelsberg was born in New York City in 1946 and is a graduate of Radcliffe College and Princeton University (where she received her Masters and PhD). She has been a faculty member of Smith College since 1972, where she teaches government and the study of women and gender. She taught one of the first courses dealing with gender at Smith College ("Women and Social Change") and has been a member of the Committee on the Study of Women and Gender and the Five College Women's Studies Committee. Her work at Smith focuses on the construction of gender and citizenship in the realm of what she calls "applied feminist theory," and the anarchist women's organization in Spain.
    In the late 1960's and early 1970's, Ackelsberg was involved in the women's health movement in New York City and student activism at Princeton during her time there as a graduate student during the years of 1968 and 1972. She has also been involved with several movements aimed at changing the status of women within the Jewish community, including the politics of changing family structures and the place of the LGBT community.
    Martha Ackelsberg currently lives with her partner, Judith Plaskow, in Northampton, Massachusetts, where she is involved with various feminist, progressive, and Jewish organizations. She and her partner contribute to current "gay marriage" debates.
    Scope and Contents
    In this oral history, Martha Ackelsberg describes her work in Jewish feminist communities and her experiences with attempts to make sense of her lesbian identity in terms of her Judaism. The interview first focuses on Ackelsberg's early observations of gender inequalities within Judaism and then moves into her work within feminist organizations such as Ezrat Nashim and B'Not Esh to try to combat those injustices. Ackelsberg's describes her feelings on current gay issues such as the word "queer," gay marriage, and the troubles that come about when defining a unified LGBT or Jewish LGBT community. The interview frames Ackelsberg's relationships both with her ex-husband and with her current partner, Judith, and investigates the intricacies involved in becoming a lesbian step-parent and the multiple definitions of family that have become central to Ackelsberg's life, passions, and academic work.
    Ackelsberg, Martha
    - Video interview of Martha Ackelsberg
    - Transcript of interview of Martha Ackelsberg (Box 1)
  - Terry Boggis interviewed by Iris Howorth, 2010 March 27; Boggis, Terry; 1 oral histories (transcript and video)
    Terry Boggis (b. 1951) was born in Schenectady, New York and moved to Denver, Colorado at the age of eight. She attended Colorado State University before moving to New York City in the late 1970s. Boggis worked in corporate communications at a consulting firm and as a media specialist at the Girl Scout Council of greater New York before becoming one of the founding members of Center Kids in 1988, the year her son was born. Since its founding, Center Families has grown to be the largest regional LGBT families program in the country. Boggis began was the Lesbian and Gay Community Services Center's Director of Communications and now serves as the Center's Interim Director of Public Policy. Boggis has written and published many articles on LGBT family issues for many New York City newspapers, including the New York Times. She has also written for Out Magazine and other gay media. Her articles and essays have appeared in many different publications and she has conducted LGBT awareness and anti-bias training in which she speaks on issues that affect nontraditional families. She is also a founding board member of Queers for Economic Justice.
    In this oral history Boggis discusses her course of life, reflecting on past romantic relationships and current relationships with her family. She tells of her experience as a lesbian mom and the work she does now for other nontraditional families. She tells of her relationship with her own parents and of her experiences as a young, recent college graduate in New York and more recently.
    Boggis, Terry
    - Video interview of Terry Boggis
    - Transcript of interview of Terry Boggis (Box 1)
  - Wendy Essery interviewed by Susannah Calhoun, 2010 April 17; Essery, Wendy; 1 oral histories (transcript and video)
    This interview is closed until January 1, 2050 unless express permission is granted by the narrator. No online access. No bio or abstract online.
    Essery, Wendy
    - Video interview of Wendy Essery
    - Transcript of interview of Wendy Essery (Box 4)
  - Deborah Faison interviewed by Lori E. Harris, 2010 March 17; Faison, Deborah; 1 oral histories (transcript and video)
    Deborah Faison (b. 1951) in Wake County, NC but raised in Philadelphia, PA. My narrator is an African American lesbian who resides in the suburbs of Washington, DC. The eldest of four children, Deborah graduated from Germantown High School in Philadelphia and matriculated into Eastern Baptist College outside of Philadelphia. She attended Eastern for only one year. Deborah's first paying job was part-time in a sandwich shop, then as a nursing aide in a nursing home. She worked at the gas company in Philadelphia as a receptionist and was promoted to customer service representative. She moved to the Washington, DC area after marrying a man that she stayed married to for 18 months.. Deborah has worked most of her life as a receptionist/secretary. Deborah is an administrative assistant with a government agency in Washington, DC where she is active in cultural programming. Last year for Black History Month she initiated postings of poetry by black poets in all of the organization's buildings. She has also organized the musical presentation of a trio of singers (she was the pianist) who performed at her institution's celebration of Martin Luther King, Jr.'s legacy. In her free time, Deborah has been involved in assisting with meetings and programs for AIDS/HIV education. She also plays the piano for church choirs in the Washington, DC area.
    In this oral history Deborah Faison describes growing up in Philadelphia, PA in the early 1960s. Although raised in a two-person household, Deborah, her siblings and her mother experienced abuse and neglect at the hands of the man that Deborah believed to be her biological father. It wasn't until she was an adult that she learned that the man she believed to be her father was actually her stepfather and had adopted her at a young age. Deborah recalls having lived part of her childhood with her two uncles. She stated that they were very instrumental in her development and she spoke of them fondly. Although Deborah married at the age of 21 and moved to Washington, DC, she soon fell in love with a woman and began a partnership with this woman that lasted for over 22 years. Her partner died unexpectedly and Deborah speaks poignantly and passionately about how her Partner Mya helped to shape Deborah's life and how it was Mya who helped Deborah gain a greater appreciation and deeper spirituality in terms of her Christian faith. When Deborah came out to her Mother her Mother rejected her and they did not speak for over 12 years. Eventually they reunited and maintain a loving and healthy relationship today. Deborah's story is unique in that it chronicles the everyday life of an African American Lesbian. Deborah became active in a Black Gay church where her perspective about homosexuality as a sin changed drastically. Deborah has a very deep faith walk and her belief system is interspersed with prophecy and visions. Although Deborah did not belong to any political or social LGBT organizations, she has lived the majority of her adult life as an out African American Lesbian. Her quiet strength, deep faith and her ability to live out her convictions in her day-to-day life is a testimony of radicalism and courage.
    Faison, Deborah
    - Video interview of Deborah Faison
    - Transcript of interview of Deborah Faison (Box 1)
  - Julie Flachs interviewed by Olivia Mandica-Hart, 2010 March 19; Flachs, Julie; 1 oral histories (transcript and video)
    Julie Flachs was born in 1975 in St. Louis and raised in Olivette, Missouri, a suburb of St. Louis. She attended the University of Michigan at Ann Arbor, earning a Bachelors Degree in Kinesiology. At Michigan, she played field hockey, served as the captain her senior year, and was both All American and Missouri Sports Woman of the Year in 1997. She also earned a Masters Degree from Endicott College in Sports Management. After graduating from Michigan, she taught physical education in the Midwest for a number of years before moving to Massachusetts.
    In this oral history, Flachs talks growing up in Missouri and living in a single-parent home with her brother. She also goes into detail about her coming out process during her first year at the University of Michigan, where she made strong bonds with her field hockey coach, and dealt with issues of isolation and depression, culminating in a suicide attempt. Flachs then describes her struggle as a lesbian and as a physical education teacher within the public school system in both the Midwest and Massachusetts. Flachs' interview is particularly strong around the issues of sexual orientation discrimination within the workforce and her personal coming out process and difficulties. Her story tells us that homophobia is still in full force, even in the Northeast.
    Flachs, Julie
    - Video interview of Julie Flachs
    - Transcript of interview of Julie Flachs (Box 1)
  - Peggy Gillespie interviewed by Alanna Dick, 2010 April 2; Gillespie, Peggy; 1 oral histories (transcript and video)
    Peggy Gillespie (b. 1948) grew up in New York City, graduated from Smith College in 1969, and has a master's degree from University of Oklahoma. She is a certified social worker and has held various jobs such as massage therapist, freelance journalist, editor, dancer and actor. Gillespie's father died when she was sixteen and she lived with her mother, grandmother and maid. Gillespie is Caucasian, grew up as a non-practicing Jew, and as an adult follows some Buddhist practices. She identifies as bisexual, has been married to men twice, and is currently in a relationship with a woman. Her first marriage at age twenty-one lasted four years and then she married her second husband at thirty and he died in 2000. Gillespie and her second husband adopted a biracial girl. Gillespie is the Co-Founder/Director of Family Diversity Projects, a non-profit in Amherst, Massachusetts. She is the Editor-in-Chief of all of Family Diversity Project's exhibits and books.
    In this oral history Peggy Gillespie describes her childhood growing up in New York City and Tenafly, New Jersey. The interview focuses on her desires, sexual attraction, and relationships through her life starting with crushes in primary school. Gillespie's story is a primary source of a bisexual women's experience with love, lust and sexual relations. The interview also includes narrative about Gillespie's second husband's death and their adopted daughter. Gillespie speaks to the experience of raising her daughter as a single parent and watching her grow up as a tomboy and then later coming out as a lesbian. Gillespie talks about founding Family Diversity Projects and the experience involved in running a non-profit. The interview provides excellent insight into bisexual identity formation and validation, as well as bisexual visibility.
    Gillespie, Peggy
    - Video interview of Peggy Gillespie
    - Transcript of interview of Peggy Gillespie (Box 1)
  - Ann Hackler interviewed by Kayden Moore, 2010 April 10; Hackler, Ann; 1 oral histories (transcript and video)
    Ann Hackler (b. 1960) grew up in Illinois and graduated from Hampshire College. Her background is in anti-racist work, especially in the women's movement. Hackler is the co-founder and Executive Director of the Institute for Musical Arts (IMA), located in Goshen, MA.
    In this oral history Ann Hackler describes growing up in a small Midwestern town in the 1960s – 70s. She speaks about her work organizing around anti-racist issues in the late 1970s on various college campuses. Later, she discusses the women's music movement, and founding the IMA with her partner June Millington in the late 1980s.
    Hackler, Ann
    - Video interview of Ann Hackler
    - Transcript of interview of Ann Hackler (Box 1)
  - Andrea Hairston interviewed by Aiden Leigh Bartelt, 2010 March 26; Hairston, Andrea; 1 oral histories (transcript and video)
    Andrea Hairston (b. 1952) grew up in Homewood in Pittsburgh, got her B.A. at Smith in 1974, and finished a graduate degree at Brown University. She has since taught at Smith, Brown, Holyoke Community College, and Trinity College. She is an artist, an actor, a playwright, a director, a musician, a poet, an academic, a teacher, an organizer and a novelist. Her published fiction includes Griots of the Galaxy, Mindscape and Redwood and Wildfire, and her plays include On Display – Do Not Touch, Polywise, Soul Repairs, and Archangels of Funk, among many others. She has also published poetry in African Voices and Chomo-Uri, as well as written a large body critical work on subjects from robot narratives to the persistence of minstrel caricatures. Having co-founded Chrysalis Theatre Company, a broad-spectrum social action theater group, in 1978, she was serving as its artistic director at the time of the interview in 2010.
    In this oral history, Andrea Hairston describes her childhood in a working-class African-American community in Pittsburgh and her experiences in community activism around Civil Rights, union organizing, and anti-war activity through her teenage years. Describing her sense of "revolving movements," she details her subsequent involvement with women's movements and queer organizing and community through her time as a student at Smith College. The interview focuses on her sense of multiple-issue activism over time, her experience of Northampton's queer, activist, and artistic community development since the '70s, her work with Chrysalis Theatre, and her relationships with her partner, Pan Welland, and James Emery in their three-person household. Hairston's stories detail how her experiences with and senses of community, collective action, and imaginative possibility have shaped both her approach to queer identity and activism in the world, making a strong contribution to these postwar histories.
    Hairston, Andrea
    - Video interview of Andrea Hairston
    - Transcript of interview of Andrea Hairston (Box 1)
  - Rebecca Lukens interviewed by Ariella Frishberg, 2010 March 14; Lukens, Rebecca; 1 oral histories (transcript and video)
    Rebecca "Becky" Lukens was born in 1960 in Lake Forest, IL and raised in Park Ridge, IL. She went to college first at Michigan State, and then transferred to the University of Oregon where she received a BS in Asian History and Education with a US History Minor before continuing on to receive an MAT from Lewis and Clark College.
    She and her partner, Lisa Dieringer, have been together for 10 years. They married in Oregon, although their marriage is no longer recognized by the state as Oregon later amended the constitution to define marriage as between one man and one woman. She never sent in the check to get the "refund" on their marriage license, so in her book that still counts. They adopted their two sons, Sam (6) and Isaac (2) from the Pacific Islands.
    During the 1980's she was politically active, and participated in marches even though sometimes she had to wear a bag over her head because the school district would have fired her. Becky was the department head of the West Linn High School's social studies department in 1992, when the elections for Measure 9 were approaching. She was outed by a journalist for the Oregonian, and although at times she worried for her life, she was also struck by the amount of support she received from the community around her. In 1993, she left West Linn and founded an alternative middle and high school with four other teachers in Portland. She is currently the co-director of the school and teaches social studies.
    In this oral history, Becky Lukens talks about growing up in the Midwest and her family's response to her coming out. She talks about her experiences during Oregon's Ballot Measure 9 campaign, and her involvement in activism because of it. In the last third of the interview, she talks about faith, and the formation of family.
    Lukens, Rebecca
    - Video interview of Rebecca Lukens
    - Transcript of interview of Rebecca Lukens (Box 2)
  - June Millington interviewed by Kimberly Bormann, 2010 April 5; Millington, June; 1 oral histories (transcript and video)